A tourist is backpacking
يجول سائح بحقيبة ظهر
through the highlands of Scotland,
عبر مرتفعات أسكتلندا،
and he stops at a pub to get a drink.
ويتوقف في حانة ليشرب.
And the only people in there is a bartender
والأشخاص الوحيدون هناك هم ساقي الحانة
and an old man nursing a beer.
وشخص عجوز يتعافى من الجعة.
And he orders a pint, and they sit in silence for a while.
ثم يطلب نصف لتر، فيجلسون في صمت للحظة.
And suddenly the old man turns to him and goes,
وفجأة يلتفت نحوه الرجل العجوز فيقول،
"You see this bar?
"هل ترى هاته الحانة؟
I built this bar with my bare hands
بنيتها بيدي هاتين
from the finest wood in the county.
من أفضل أنواع الخشب في البلد.
Gave it more love and care than my own child.
أعطيتها حبا ورعاية أكثر من طفلي الخاص.
But do they call me MacGregor the bar builder? No."
لكن هل ينادونني بماكجريجور باني الحانة؟ لا."
Points out the window.
يشير إلى النافذة.
"You see that stone wall out there?
"هل ترى الجدار الحجري هناك؟
I built that stone wall with my bare hands.
لقد بنيت ذلك الجدار الحجري بيدي هاتين.
Found every stone, placed them just so through the rain and the cold.
وجدت كل صخرة، ووضعتها كما هي خلال المطر والبرد.
But do they call me MacGregor the stone wall builder? No."
لكن هل ينادونني بماكجريجور باني الجدار الحجري؟ لا."
Points out the window.
يشير إلى النافذة.
"You see that pier on the lake out there?
"هل ترى ذلك الرصيف على البحيرة هناك خارجا؟
I built that pier with my bare hands.
لقد بنيت ذلك الرصيف بيدي هاتين.
Drove the pilings against the tide of the sand, plank by plank.
واضعا الدعائم لمواجهة التيار لوحا لوحا.
But do they call me MacGregor the pier builder? No.
لكن هل ينادونني بماكجريجور باني الرصيف؟ لا.
But you fuck one goat ... "
لكن تنكح نعجة واحدة .."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Storytelling --
سرد القصص --
is joke telling.
هو سرد للنكت.
It's knowing your punchline,
هو أن تعرف الجزء المضحك لديك،
your ending,
نهايتك،
knowing that everything you're saying, from the first sentence to the last,
أن تعرف أن كل شيء تقوله، من أول جملة إلى آخرها،
is leading to a singular goal,
يقود إلى هدف واحد،
and ideally confirming some truth
وبطريقة مثالية، تأكيد بعض الحقيقة
that deepens our understandings
التي تعمق فهمنا
of who we are as human beings.
لما نحن عليه كبشر.
We all love stories.
كلنا نحب القصص.
We're born for them.
لقد ولدنا من أجلها.
Stories affirm who we are.
القصص تثبث ما نحن عليه.
We all want affirmations that our lives have meaning.
كلنا نريد إثباتات على أن حياتنا لها مغزى.
And nothing does a greater affirmation
ولا شيء أكثر يقوم بالإثبات
than when we connect through stories.
من حين نرتبط عبر القصص.
It can cross the barriers of time,
يمكنها أن تتجاوز حدود الزمن،
past, present and future,
الماضي والحاضر والمستقبل،
and allow us to experience
وتسمح لنا بتجربة
the similarities between ourselves
أوجه التشابه بيننا
and through others, real and imagined.
ومن خلال الآخرين، الحقيقيين والمتخيلين.
The children's television host Mr. Rogers
مضيف برامج الأطفال السيد روجرز
always carried in his wallet
كان دائما يحمل معه في حافظته
a quote from a social worker
اقتباسا من عامل اجتماعي
that said, "Frankly, there isn't anyone you couldn't learn to love
يقول، "بصراحة، ليس هناك أي شخص لن تستطيع تعلم حبه
once you've heard their story."
حين تسمع قصته."
And the way I like to interpret that
والطريقة التي أود بها أن أفسر بها ذلك
is probably the greatest story commandment,
هو أنه ربما أعظم وصية للقصة
which is "Make me care" --
والتي هي "اجعلني أهتم" --
please, emotionally,
رجاء، عاطفيا،
intellectually, aesthetically,
وفكريا وجماليا،
just make me care.
فقط اجعلني أهتم.
We all know what it's like to not care.
جميعنا نعرف ما يعنيه ألا تهتم.
You've gone through hundreds of TV channels,
تمر عبر مئات القنوات التلفزيونية،
just switching channel after channel,
فقط تنتقل من قناة لأخرى،
and then suddenly you actually stop on one.
وفجأة تتوقف فعلا في واحدة.
It's already halfway over,
هي بالفعل في منتصف الطريق،
but something's caught you and you're drawn in and you care.
لكن هناك شيء قد جذب انتباهك وأنت تهتم.
That's not by chance,
ليس تلك صدفة،
that's by design.
ذلك تصميم.
So it got me thinking, what if I told you my history was story,
وبالتالي جعلني هذا أفكر، ماذا لو أخبرتكم أن تاريخي كان قصة،
how I was born for it,
كيف ولدت من أجل ذلك،
how I learned along the way this subject matter?
وكيف تعلمت في الطريق هاته المسألة؟
And to make it more interesting,
ولجعلها أكثر إثارة للاهتمام،
we'll start from the ending
سنبدأ من النهاية
and we'll go to the beginning.
وسنذهب للبداية.
And so if I were going to give you the ending of this story,
وبالتالي إن كنت لأعطيكم نهاية هاته القصة،
it would go something like this:
ستكون شيء من هذا القبيل:
And that's what ultimately led me
وهذا ما قادني في النهاية
to speaking to you here at TED
إلى الحديث إليكم هنا في تيد
about story.
حول قصة.
And the most current story lesson that I've had
وآخر درس تلقيته
was completing the film I've just done
كان إنهاء الفيلم الذي أنهيته للتو
this year in 2012.
هذه السنة 2012.
The film is "John Carter." It's based on a book called "The Princess of Mars,"
الفيلم هو "جون كارتر" وهو يعتمد على كتاب يدعى "أميرة المريخ،"
which was written by Edgar Rice Burroughs.
والذي ألفه إدغار رايس بوروز.
And Edgar Rice Burroughs actually put himself
وإدغار رايس بوروز قد وضع نفسه بالفعل
as a character inside this movie, and as the narrator.
كشخصية داخل هذا الفيلم، وكراو.
And he's summoned by his rich uncle, John Carter, to his mansion
وقد تم استدعاؤه من طرف عمه الغني، جون كارتر، إلى قصره
with a telegram saying, "See me at once."
ببرقية تقول "قابلني فورا."
But once he gets there,
لكن بمجرد وصوله إلى هناك،
he's found out that his uncle has mysteriously passed away
وجد أن عمه قد توفي في ظروف غامضة
and been entombed in a mausoleum on the property.
وتم دفنه في ضريح في الملكية العقارية.
(Video) Butler: You won't find a keyhole.
(فيديو) وصيف: لن تجد ثقب المفتاح.
Thing only opens from the inside.
هذا يفتح من الداخل فقط.
He insisted,
أصر على ذلك،
no embalming, no open coffin,
لا تحنيط ولا كفن مفتوح،
no funeral.
ولا جنازة.
You don't acquire the kind of wealth your uncle commanded
لا تتلقى مقدار ثروة عمك
by being like the rest of us, huh?
بكونك مثل بقيتنا، صحيح؟
Come, let's go inside.
تعال، لنذهب إلى الداخل.
AS: What this scene is doing, and it did in the book,
أ.س: ما يقوم به هذا المشهد وما قام به في الكتاب،
is it's fundamentally making a promise.
هو أساسا تقديم وعد.
It's making a promise to you
تقدم لكم وعدا
that this story will lead somewhere that's worth your time.
أن هذه القصة ستقود إلى مكان يستحق وقتكم.
And that's what all good stories should do at the beginning, is they should give you a promise.
وهذا ما يجب أن تقوم به كل القصص الجيدة في البداية، يجب أن تعطيك وعدا.
You could do it an infinite amount of ways.
يمكن أن تقوم بذلك بعدد غير محدود من الطرق.
Sometimes it's as simple as "Once upon a time ... "
أحيانا يكون بمثل بساطة "كان يا ما كان ..."
These Carter books always had Edgar Rice Burroughs as a narrator in it.
كتب كارت هاته دائما ما يكون فيها إدغار رايس بوروز راويا.
And I always thought it was such a fantastic device.
ودائما ما فكرت أنه جهاز رائع.
It's like a guy inviting you around the campfire,
إنه مثل شخص يدعوكم حول نار المخيم،
or somebody in a bar saying, "Here, let me tell you a story.
أو أحدهم في الحانة يقول، "هنا، دعني أخبرك بقصة.
It didn't happen to me, it happened to somebody else,
لم تحصل لي، حصلت لشخص آخر،
but it's going to be worth your time."
لكنها ستستحق وقتك."
A well told promise
وعد مصرح عنه جيدا
is like a pebble being pulled back in a slingshot
هو مثل حصاة يجري سحبها من مقلاع
and propels you forward through the story
ويدفع بك تقدما في القصة
to the end.
إلى النهاية.
In 2008,
سنة 2008،
I pushed all the theories that I had on story at the time
دفعت بكل النظريات التي كانت لدي حول القصة
to the limits of my understanding on this project.
إلى حدود فهمي لهذا المشروع.
(Video) (Mechanical Sounds)
(فيديو) (صوت ميكانيكي)
♫ And that is all ♫
♫وهذا كل ♫
♫ that love's about ♫
♫ما هو عليه الحب♫
♫ And we'll recall ♫
♫وجميعنا نتذكر♫
♫ when time runs out ♫
♫حين تنقضي الأوقات♫
♫ That it only ♫
♫أنها فقط♫
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
AS: Storytelling without dialogue.
أ.س: رواية القصص من دون حوار.
It's the purest form of cinematic storytelling.
إنه الشكل الأصفي من رواية القصص السينمائية.
It's the most inclusive approach you can take.
إنها المقاربة الأكثر شمولية التي قد تعتمدها.
It confirmed something I really had a hunch on,
لقد أكدت شيء كان عندي حدس بخصوصه،
is that the audience
وهو أن الجمهور
actually wants to work for their meal.
يريد حقا أن يعملوا من أجل طعامهم.
They just don't want to know that they're doing that.
هم فقط لا يريدون أن يعرفوا أنهم يقومون بذلك.
That's your job as a storyteller,
تلك مهمتك كراو للقصة،
is to hide the fact
أن تخفي حقيقة
that you're making them work for their meal.
أنك تجعلهم يعملون من أجل طعامهم.
We're born problem solvers.
نحن ولدنا كحلالي مشاكل.
We're compelled to deduce
نحن مجبرون على الاستنتاج
and to deduct,
وعلى الاقتطاع،
because that's what we do in real life.
لأن ذلك ما نفعله في الحياة الحقيقية.
It's this well-organized absence of information
إن هذا الفقدان المنظم للغاية للمعلومة
that draws us in.
هو ما يجذبنا.
There's a reason that we're all attracted to an infant or a puppy.
هناك سبب يجعلنا ننجذب نحو رضيع أو جرو.
It's not just that they're damn cute;
ليس فقط لأنهم في غاية الجاذبية؛
it's because they can't completely express
بل لأنهم لا يستطيعون التعبير بشكل كامل
what they're thinking and what their intentions are.
عما يفكرون فيه وعن نواياهم.
And it's like a magnet.
ذلك مثل مغناطيس.
We can't stop ourselves
لا نستطيع إمساك أنفسنا
from wanting to complete the sentence and fill it in.
عن الرغبة في إتمام الجملة وإنهائها.
I first started
بدأت أولا
really understanding this storytelling device
في فهم وسيلة رواية القصص حقا
when I was writing with Bob Peterson on "Finding Nemo."
حين كنت أكتب "البحث عن نيمو" مع بوب بيترسون
And we would call this the unifying theory of two plus two.
ونستطيع أن نسمي هذه بالنظرية الموحدة لاثنين زائد اثنين.
Make the audience put things together.
اجعل الجمهور يضع الأمور على بعضها.
Don't give them four,
لا تعطهم أربعة،
give them two plus two.
أعطهم اثنين زائد اثنين.
The elements you provide and the order you place them in
العناصر التي توفرها والترتيب الذي تجعلها عليه
is crucial to whether you succeed or fail at engaging the audience.
هي حتمية في مدى نجاحك أو فشلك في إشراك الجمهور.
Editors and screenwriters have known this all along.
المحررون وكتاب السيناريو عرفوا هذا من قبل.
It's the invisible application
إنه التطبيق الخفي
that holds our attention to story.
الذي يعلق اهتمامنا بالقصة.
I don't mean to make it sound
لا أقصد جعله يبدو
like this is an actual exact science, it's not.
وكأن هذا بالفعل علم مضبوط، هو ليس كذلك.
That's what's so special about stories,
هذا ما هو مميز بخصوص القصص،
they're not a widget, they aren't exact.
هي ليست بالقطع، ليست مضبوطة.
Stories are inevitable, if they're good,
القصص لا مفر منها، إن كانت جيدة،
but they're not predictable.
لكنها غير قابلة للتوقع.
I took a seminar in this year
أخذت حلقة دراسية هذه السنة
with an acting teacher named Judith Weston.
مع معلمة تمثيل تدعى جوديث ويستون.
And I learned a key insight to character.
وقد تعلمت بصيرة أساسية للشخصية.
She believed that all well-drawn characters
تعتقد أن الشخصيات المرسومة بعناية
have a spine.
لديها عمود فقري.
And the idea is that the character has an inner motor,
والفكرة أن الشخصية لديها محرك داخلي،
a dominant, unconscious goal that they're striving for,
هدف مهيمن لا واعي تكافح من أجله،
an itch that they can't scratch.
حكة لا يستطيعون خدشها.
She gave a wonderful example of Michael Corleone,
أعطتني مثالا رائعا لمايكل كورليوني،
Al Pacino's character in "The Godfather,"
شخصية آل باتشينو في "العراب،"
and that probably his spine
وأنه على الأرجح عموده الفقري
was to please his father.
كان هو إرضاء والده.
And it's something that always drove all his choices.
وهو شيء لطالما تحكم في خياراته.
Even after his father died,
حتى وبعد وفاة والده،
he was still trying to scratch that itch.
كان لا يزال يحاول خدش الحكة.
I took to this like a duck to water.
أخذت هذا كالبطة على الماء.
Wall-E's was to find the beauty.
فيلم وال-إي كان لإيجاد الجمال.
Marlin's, the father in "Finding Nemo,"
وبالنسبة لمارلين، الأب في "البحث عن نيمو"
was to prevent harm.
كان أن يجنب الأذى.
And Woody's was to do what was best for his child.
وبالنسبة لوودي كان أن يقوم بما هو أفضل لطفله.
And these spines don't always drive you to make the best choices.
وهذه الأعمدة الفقرية لا تدفعك دائما إلى اتخاذ أفضل القرارات.
Sometimes you can make some horrible choices with them.
أحيانا يمكن أن تتخذ بسببها قرارات فظيعة.
I'm really blessed to be a parent,
أنا بالفعل مبارك كوني والدا،
and watching my children grow, I really firmly believe
وبمشاهدة طفلي ينمو، أعتقد بحق
that you're born with a temperament and you're wired a certain way,
أن المرء يولد بمزاج وأنك موصل بطريقة معينة،
and you don't have any say about it,
وليس لديك أي رأي في الموضوع،
and there's no changing it.
وليس هناك طريقة لتغييره.
All you can do is learn to recognize it
كل ما يمكن أن تقوم به هو أن تتعلم الاعتراف به
and own it.
وامتلاكه.
And some of us are born with temperaments that are positive,
وبعضنا ولد بمزاج إيجابي،
some are negative.
والبعض سلبي.
But a major threshold is passed
لكن يتم تجاوز عتبة كبرى
when you mature enough
حين ننضج بما فيه الكفاية
to acknowledge what drives you
لنقر بما يدفعنا
and to take the wheel and steer it.
وأن نأخذ بعجلة القيادة ونوجهها.
As parents, you're always learning who your children are.
كوالدين، أنتم تتعلمون دائما من هم أطفالكم.
They're learning who they are.
إنهم يتعلمون من هم.
And you're still learning who you are.
ولا تزالون تتعلمون من أنتم.
So we're all learning all the time.
وبالتالي جميعنا نتعلم طوال الوقت.
And that's why change is fundamental in story.
وبسبب هذا فإن التغيير أساسي في القصة.
If things go static, stories die,
إن ظلت الأمور ثابتة، تموت القصص،
because life is never static.
لأن الحياة ليست أبدا ثابتة.
In 1998,
سنة 1998،
I had finished writing "Toy Story" and "A Bug's Life"
كنت قد أنهيت كتابة "حكاية لعبة" و "حياة حشرة"
and I was completely hooked on screenwriting.
وقد كنت مدمنا جدا لكتابة السيناريوهات.
So I wanted to become much better at it and learn anything I could.
وبالتالي أردت أن أصبح أفضل بكثير في المجال وأن أتعلم أي شيء أستطيع.
So I researched everything I possibly could.
وبالتالي بحثت عن كل ما قد أستطيع.
And I finally came across this fantastic quote
وفي النهاية وجدت هذه المقولة الرائعة
by a British playwright, William Archer:
من طرف الكاتب المسرحي البريطاني وليام آرتشر:
"Drama is anticipation
"الدراما هي التوقع
mingled with uncertainty."
مختلطة بعدم اليقين."
It's an incredibly insightful definition.
إنه تعريف متبصر للغاية.
When you're telling a story,
حين تروي قصة،
have you constructed anticipation?
هل بنيت أي توقعات؟
In the short-term, have you made me want to know
في المدى القصير، هل جعلتني أرغب في معرفة
what will happen next?
ما الذي سيحدث تاليا؟
But more importantly,
لكن وبشكل أهم،
have you made me want to know
هل جعلتني أرغب في معرفة
how it will all conclude in the long-term?
كيف ستخلص في المدى الطويل؟
Have you constructed honest conflicts
هل بنيت صراعات صريحة
with truth that creates doubt
مع الحقيقة تقوم بإثارة الشك
in what the outcome might be?
حول ما ستكون عليه النتيجة؟
An example would be in "Finding Nemo,"
في "البحث عن نيمو" هناك مثال على هذا
in the short tension, you were always worried,
في التوتر القصير، تكون دائما قلقا،
would Dory's short-term memory
هل ذاكرة دوري القصيرة المدى
make her forget whatever she was being told by Marlin.
ستجعله ينسى أيا كان ما قاله لها مارلين.
But under that was this global tension
وخلف ذلك كان هناك توتر أكبر
of will we ever find Nemo
حول ما إذا كنا سنجد نيمو على الإطلاق
in this huge, vast ocean?
في هذا المحيط الضخم الرحب؟
In our earliest days at Pixar,
في أيامنا الأولى في بيكسار،
before we truly understood the invisible workings of story,
قبل أن نكون قد فهمنا أساليب العمل الخفية للقصة،
we were simply a group of guys just going on our gut, going on our instincts.
كنا ببساطة مجموعة من الأشخاص نعتمد على حدسنا، نعتمد على غريزتنا.
And it's interesting to see
ومن المثير للاهتمام أن نرى
how that led us places
كيف قادنا ذلك إلى أمكان
that were actually pretty good.
كانت في الواقع جيدة للغاية.
You've got to remember that in this time of year,
عليك أن تتذكر أنه في هذا الوقت من السنة،
1993,
سنة 1993،
what was considered a successful animated picture
ما كان يعتبر رسوما متحركة ناجحة
was "The Little Mermaid," "Beauty and the Beast,"
كان "الحورية الصغيرة" و"الجميلة والوحش،"
"Aladdin," "Lion King."
"علاء الدين" "الأسد الملك."
So when we pitched "Toy Story" to Tom Hanks for the first time,
وبالتالي حين عرضنا "حكاية لعبة" على توم هانكس للمرة الأولى،
he walked in and he said,
أتانا مشيا وقال،
"You don't want me to sing, do you?"
"أنت لا تريدني أن أغني، أليس كذلك؟"
And I thought that epitomized perfectly
وفكرت في أن ذلك قد لخص بشكل مثالي
what everybody thought animation had to be at the time.
ما اعتقد الجميع أن الرسوم المتحركة يجب أن تكون عليه آنذاك.
But we really wanted to prove
لكننا أردنا فعلا أن نثبت
that you could tell stories completely different in animation.
أنه يمكنك أن تروي قصصا بطريقة مختلفة تماما بالرسوم المتحركة.
We didn't have any influence then,
لم يكن لدينا أي تأثير آنذاك،
so we had a little secret list of rules
وبالتالي كانت لدينا قائمة سرية من القواعد
that we kept to ourselves.
أبقينا عليها لأنفسنا.
And they were: No songs,
وقد كانت: بدون أغاني،
no "I want" moment,
بدون لحظات "أريد"،
no happy village,
بدون قرى سعيدة،
no love story.
بدون قصة حب.
And the irony is that, in the first year,
والسخرية كانت، أنه في السنة الأولى،
our story was not working at all
لم تكن قصتنا تعمل على الإطلاق
and Disney was panicking.
وديزني كانت في هلع.
So they privately got advice
وبالتالي قاموا سرا بطلب النصح
from a famous lyricist, who I won't name,
من شاعر غنائي شهير، لن أسميه،
and he faxed them some suggestions.
وقد أرسل لهم بعض الاقتراحات بالفاكس.
And we got a hold of that fax.
وقد حصلنا على ذلك الفاكس.
And the fax said,
وهو يقول،
there should be songs,
يجب أن تكون هناك أغاني،
there should be an "I want" song,
يجب أن تكون هناك أغنية "أريد"،
there should be a happy village song,
يجب أن تكون هناك أغاني قرية سعيدة،
there should be a love story
يجب أن تكون هناك قصة حب
and there should be a villain.
ويجب أن يكون هناك شرير.
And thank goodness
والشكر لله
we were just too young, rebellious and contrarian at the time.
أننا كنا يافعين جدا وثوريين ومناقضين آنذاك.
That just gave us more determination
أن زادنا ذلك إصرارا
to prove that you could build a better story.
على إثبات أنه يمكن أن تبني قصة أفضل.
And a year after that, we did conquer it.
وبعد سنة من ذلك، قمنا بغزو ذلك.
And it just went to prove
وكان ذلك فقط لإثبات
that storytelling has guidelines,
أن رواية القصص لديها توجيهات،
not hard, fast rules.
وليس قواعد سريعة وصارمة.
Another fundamental thing we learned
أمر آخر مهم تعلمناه
was about liking your main character.
هو بخصوص الإعجاب بالشخصية الرئيسية.
And we had naively thought,
وقد اعتقدنا بسذاجة،
well Woody in "Toy Story" has to become selfless at the end,
حسنا وودي في "حكاية لعبة" قد صار غير أناني في النهاية،
so you've got to start from someplace.
وبالتالي عليك أن تبدأ من مكان ما.
So let's make him selfish. And this is what you get.
إذن دعونا نجعله أنانيا. وهذا ما تحصل عليه.
(Voice Over) Woody: What do you think you're doing?
(صوت) وودي: ما الذي تظن نفسك فاعلا؟
Off the bed.
انزل من السرير.
Hey, off the bed!
هيا، انزل من السرير!
Mr. Potato Head: You going to make us, Woody?
السيد رأس البطاطس: هل ستجعلنا ننزل يا وودي؟
Woody: No, he is.
وودي: لا، لكنه سيفعل.
Slinky? Slink ... Slinky!
سلينكي؟ سلينك.. سلينكي!
Get up here and do your job.
تعال هنا وقم بعملك.
Are you deaf?
هل أنت أصم؟
I said, take care of them.
قلت، اهتم بأمرهم.
Slinky: I'm sorry, Woody,
سلينكي: أنا آسف يا وودي
but I have to agree with them.
لكن علي أن أوافقهم الرأي.
I don't think what you did was right.
لا أظن أن ما فعلته صائب.
Woody: What? Am I hearing correctly?
وودي: ماذا؟ هل أسمعك كما يجب؟
You don't think I was right?
لا تظنني كنت صائبا؟
Who said your job was to think, Spring Wiener?
من قال أن مهمتك أن تفكر، سبرينغ وينر؟
AS: So how do you make a selfish character likable?
أ.س: إذن كيف تجعل شخصية أنانية مثيرة للإعجاب؟
We realized, you can make him kind,
أدركنا أنه يمكننا جعله طيبا،
generous, funny, considerate,
معطاء ومضحكا ومراعيا
as long as one condition is met for him,
مادام شرط واحد متحققا فيه،
is that he stays the top toy.
أن يبقى على رأس اللعب.
And that's what it really is,
وهذا ما هو في الواقع عليه،
is that we all live life conditionally.
أننا جميعا نعيش الحياة بشروط.
We're all willing to play by the rules and follow things along,
جميعنا راغبون في اللعب وفقا للقواعد ومتابعة الأمور،
as long as certain conditions are met.
ما دامت بعض الشروط مستوفاة.
After that, all bets are off.
بعد ذلك، كل الرهانات ملغاة.
And before I'd even decided to make storytelling my career,
وقبل حتى أن أقرر جعل رواية القصص مهنتي،
I can now see key things that happened in my youth
أستطيع الآن أن أرى أمورا محورية حصلت في شبابي
that really sort of opened my eyes
قامت بالفعل بفتح عيني نوعا ما
to certain things about story.
على أمور معينة بخصوص القصة.
In 1986, I truly understood the notion
سنة 1986، فهمت تماما مبدأ
of story having a theme.
توفر القصة على فكرة رئيسية.
And that was the year that they restored and re-released
وكانت تلك السنة التي استرجعوا فيها وأعادوا إنتاج
"Lawrence of Arabia."
"لورانس العرب."
And I saw that thing seven times in one month.
وقد شاهدت ذلك سبع مرات في شهر واحد.
I couldn't get enough of it.
لم أستطع أن أشبع نفسي منه.
I could just tell there was a grand design under it --
أستطيع فقط القول أنه هناك تصميم عظيم وراءه --
in every shot, every scene, every line.
في كل لقطة وفي كل مشهد وفي كل سطر.
Yet, on the surface it just seemed
ومع ذلك، على الواجهة يبدو أنه يقوم فقط
to be depicting his historical lineage
بتصوير ذريته التاريخية
of what went on.
لما قد حصل.
Yet, there was something more being said. What exactly was it?
ومع ذلك، كان هناك أشياء أكثر تقال. ما الذي كان ذلك بالضبط؟
And it wasn't until, on one of my later viewings,
ولم يتغير ذلك إلى غاية أحد مشاهداتي اللاحقة،
that the veil was lifted
حين تم كشف الحجاب
and it was in a scene where he's walked across the Sinai Desert
وقد كان ذلك في مشهد حيث مشى عبر صحراء سيناء
and he's reached the Suez Canal,
وقد وصل إلى قناة السويس،
and I suddenly got it.
وفجأة أدركت الأمر.
(Video) Boy: Hey! Hey! Hey! Hey!
(فيديو) ولد: مهلا! مهلا! مهلا! مهلا! مهلا!
Cyclist: Who are you?
دراج: من أنت؟
Who are you?
من أنت؟
AS: That was the theme: Who are you?
أ.س: كانت تلك الفكرة العامة: من أنت؟
Here were all these seemingly disparate
هنا كانت كل هذه الحوارات والأحداث
events and dialogues
التي تبدو متباينة
that just were chronologically telling the history of him,
والتي كانت فقط تخبرنا زمنيا بقصته،
but underneath it was a constant,
لكن وراءها كانت ثابتة،
a guideline, a road map.
خط موجه وخريطة طريق.
Everything Lawrence did in that movie
كل ما قام به لورانس في الفيلم
was an attempt for him to figure out where his place was in the world.
كان محاولة منه لمعرفة مكانه في العالم.
A strong theme is always running through
فكرة عامة قوية دائما تمر عبر
a well-told story.
قصة مروية بشكل جيد.
When I was five,
حين كنت في الخامسة من عمري،
I was introduced to possibly the most major ingredient
وقد تم تعريفي على أهم وأكبر مكون
that I feel a story should have,
أعتقد أن القصة تحتاجه،
but is rarely invoked.
لكن نادرا ما يتم استدعاءه.
And this is what my mother took me to when I was five.
وهذا ما أخذتني إليه أمي حين كنت في الخامسة من عمري.
(Video) Thumper: Come on. It's all right.
(فيديو) ثامبر: تعال. إنه على ما يرام.
Look.
انظر.
The water's stiff.
الماء يابس.
Bambi: Yippee!
بامبي: ييبي!
Thumper: Some fun,
ثامبر: ياله من مرح،
huh, Bambi?
أليس كذلك بامبي؟
Come on. Get up.
تعال. توقف.
Like this.
هكذا.
Ha ha. No, no, no.
ها ها. لا، لا، لا.
AS: I walked out of there
أ.س: خرجت من هناك
wide-eyed with wonder.
بعينين واسعتين من الاندهاش.
And that's what I think the magic ingredient is,
وهذا ما أظن أنه المكون السحري،
the secret sauce,
الصلصة السرية،
is can you invoke wonder.
هو هل تستطيع أن تثير الاندهاش.
Wonder is honest, it's completely innocent.
الاندهاش يكون صادقا، هو بريء بالكامل.
It can't be artificially evoked.
لا يمكن أن تستثار اصطناعيا.
For me, there's no greater ability
بالنسبة لي، ليست هناك قدرة أعظم
than the gift of another human being giving you that feeling --
من هبة أن يعطيك شخص آخر ذلك الإحساس--
to hold them still just for a brief moment in their day
أن تمسك بهم للحظة وجيزة في يومهم
and have them surrender to wonder.
وأنت تجعلهم يستسلمون للدهشة.
When it's tapped, the affirmation of being alive,
إثبات الحياة حين يتم استغلاله،
it reaches you almost to a cellular level.
يوصلك إلى مستوى شبه خلوي.
And when an artist does that to another artist,
وحين يقوم فنان بذلك لفنان آخر،
it's like you're compelled to pass it on.
تحس وكأنك مجبر على تمرير ذلك.
It's like a dormant command
إنه كأمر نائم
that suddenly is activated in you, like a call to Devil's Tower.
يتم فجأة تفعيله فيك، مثل نداء لبرج الشيطان.
Do unto others what's been done to you.
أن تفعل بالآخرين ما فعل بك.
The best stories infuse wonder.
أفضل القصص تبث الدهشة.
When I was four years old,
حين كنت في سن الرابعة،
I have a vivid memory
لدي ذاكرة قوية
of finding two pinpoint scars on my ankle
في إيجاد وتحديد ندبين على ساقي
and asking my dad what they were.
وسؤال والدي بخصوصها.
And he said I had a matching pair like that on my head,
وقد قال أنه لدي اثنان مشابهان على رأسي،
but I couldn't see them because of my hair.
لكنني لم أستطع رؤيتهما بسبب شعري.
And he explained that when I was born,
وشرح أنه حين ولدت،
I was born premature,
ولدت قبل أواني،
that I came out much too early,
أنني خرجت مبكرا جدا،
and I wasn't fully baked;
ولم أكن مخبوزا بالكامل؛
I was very, very sick.
كنت مريضا للغاية.
And when the doctor took a look at this yellow kid with black teeth,
وحين نظر الطبيب إلى هذا الطفل الأصفر ذي الأسنان السوداء،
he looked straight at my mom and said,
نظر مباشرة إلى أمي وقال،
"He's not going to live."
"لن يستطيع الحياة."
And I was in the hospital for months.
وقد كنت في المستشفي لأشهر.
And many blood transfusions later,
وبعد عدة عمليات نقل دم،
I lived,
عشت،
and that made me special.
وهذا جعلني مميزا.
I don't know if I really believe that.
لا أعرف إن كنت أصدق ذلك فعلا.
I don't know if my parents really believe that,
لا أعرف إن كان والداي فعلا يصدقان ذلك،
but I didn't want to prove them wrong.
لكن لم أرد أن أثبت خطأهم.
Whatever I ended up being good at,
أيا كان ما صرت خبيرا فيه،
I would strive to be worthy of the second chance I was given.
سأسعى جاهدا لأستحق الفرصة الثانية التي أعطيت لي.
(Video) (Crying)
(فيديو) (بكاء)
Marlin: There, there, there.
مارلين: هون عليك.
It's okay, daddy's here.
الأمر على ما يرام، أبوك موجود هنا.
Daddy's got you.
أبوك سيحميك.
I promise,
أعدك،
I will never let anything happen to you, Nemo.
لن أدع أي شيء يحصل لك أبدا، نيمو.
AS: And that's the first story lesson I ever learned.
أ.س: وذلك كان أول درس قصة تعلمته.
Use what you know. Draw from it.
استخدم ما تعرفه. وارسم من خلاله.
It doesn't always mean plot or fact.
لا يعني دائما حقيقة أم مؤامرة.
It means capturing a truth from your experiencing it,
يعني التقاط حقيقة من تجربتك لها،
expressing values you personally feel
أن تعبر عن قيم أحسست بها شخصيا
deep down in your core.
عميقا في جوهرك.
And that's what ultimately led me to speaking to you
وهذا ما جعلني في الأخير أتحدث إليكم
here at TEDTalk today.
هنا في محادثة تيد اليوم.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)